<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="//localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="//localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="//localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-08T21:13:53-05:00</updated><id>//localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Mahir Chowdhury</title><subtitle>Electrical Engineering Student</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Whiteboard</title><link href="//localhost:4000/whiteboard/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Whiteboard" /><published>2020-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>//localhost:4000/whiteboard</id><content type="html" xml:base="//localhost:4000/whiteboard/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mahirchow/Whiteboard&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-primary&quot;&gt;Visit Github Repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whiteboard-student-improvement-application&quot;&gt;Whiteboard (Student Improvement Application)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This application was initially developed for the Windsor Engineering Competition of 2020 by team No-Name (Mahir Chowdhury, Ahmad Ali, Ghenwa Altabbaa). The theme for this competition was to create a study enhancement application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technologies used: Qt for Python, Numpy, Pandas, XLSX, Os&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scenario&quot;&gt;Scenario&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Online school has been a difficult transition for all students this year, and with the third semester of online school just around the corner students could use more help getting their schoolworkdone. Therefore,the University of Windsor hasrequested that your software firm develop a custom learning app to help students’study and work more effectively and efficiently. Toreduce the number of late assignments received by professors, the University has requested that the app include an Automatic Scheduling program to help students stay organized and up to date with schoolwork. It must also includea virtual flash card program,which will help students to study and memorize course content efficiently the night before their exams. Upon reviewing the average of the latest Integral Calculus course, the University has also recommended that an integral calculator be added to the program. Your team is also encouraged to include any additional programs that might benefit students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Retrieved from the official Programming Competitor Handout for WEC 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-demo-of-project&quot;&gt;Video Demo of Project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Qo6Zxk7FGaU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;featured-images-of-application&quot;&gt;Featured Images of Application&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/33791954/107157426-1249e700-6952-11eb-8dfb-3b42ca08b180.png&quot; alt=&quot;dashboard&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/33791954/107157433-16760480-6952-11eb-85bf-f8e5d7c4e344.png&quot; alt=&quot;calendar&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/33791954/107157435-183fc800-6952-11eb-8501-fbef82f3f284.png&quot; alt=&quot;flashcards&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/33791954/107157436-1a098b80-6952-11eb-89dd-4dd1bab9b3bb.png&quot; alt=&quot;calculator&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I will likely improve this project by replacing the current calculator tab with a wolfram alpha api interface as that will vastly improve the usefulness of this software.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I may additionally revamp the user interface and make it more modern.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making the process of editing the calendar, schedule, and todo list a lot simpler and intuitive. Maybe even have it work with apis like Google Calendar or even College Schedule maker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installation&quot;&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clone the repository&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create virtual environment (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pip install requirements.txt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;run the main.py file through your terminal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="python" /><category term="qt" /><category term="pandas" /><summary type="html">A student improvement desktop application designed to aid students with their studying.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Directory Sweeper</title><link href="//localhost:4000/directory-sweeper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Directory Sweeper" /><published>2020-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>//localhost:4000/directory-sweeper</id><content type="html" xml:base="//localhost:4000/directory-sweeper/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mahirchow/Directory-Sweeper&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-primary&quot;&gt;Visit Github Repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GBd65n8Dnss&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inspiration&quot;&gt;Inspiration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My folders are always messy. That’s why I decided to program a solution to this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-it-does&quot;&gt;What it does&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start the program, it asks for a cluttered directory to organize. Once you click it, it’ll immediately begin organizing the directory. It will create an organized folder and within it, it’ll have a folder for every file type [Text Files, Video Files, Image Files, etc].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-i-built-it&quot;&gt;How I built it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This software was programmed with Python and Qt for Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges-i-ran-into&quot;&gt;Challenges I ran into&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not many other than having to manually make long lists of file extension types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;accomplishments-that-im-proud-of&quot;&gt;Accomplishments that I’m proud of&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a working software that can be used on any platform. I’m proud that this can be used right away by people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-i-learned&quot;&gt;What I learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learned a bit more about the shutil library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next-for-folder-organizer&quot;&gt;What’s next for Folder Organizer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe I’ll make a better user interface and more customizability so users can customize how their folders are organized.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="python" /><category term="qt" /><summary type="html">A utility tool which organizes all the files in a directory.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Covid-19 Global</title><link href="//localhost:4000/covid19-global/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Covid-19 Global" /><published>2020-07-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>//localhost:4000/covid19-global</id><content type="html" xml:base="//localhost:4000/covid19-global/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mahirchow/COVID-19-GLOBAL&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-info&quot;&gt;Visit Github Repo&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://devpost.com/software/covid-19-global&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-info&quot;&gt;Visit Devpost&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;inspiration&quot;&gt;Inspiration:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our idea was brought about by the need to address the concerns that we share about the ongoing Coronavirus pandemic. Particularly, we felt concerned with the spread of information. Among the innumerous online sources which cover Covid-19 material, it is sometimes difficult for the average person to find the exact information they want or know whether it is always coming from a trusted news source. With this in mind, we decided to create our own platform for Covid-19 information that would provide current and trustworthy facts and figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xbPZWd21G2g&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-it-does&quot;&gt;What it does:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our project is a desktop application which begins by displaying the current Covid-19 values for the World. These include the total number of cases and deaths, as well as the new number of cases and deaths for the current day. The user then has the option to type into a search bar the name of the country they wish to receive more specific information on. The application would then direct to a new screen where the country flag is generated along with the current Covid-19 facts, health statistics, and demographic values for that country. Furthermore, the user can click on any on the daily Covid-19 values to be redirected to another screen which displays a graph of all recorded values for the country since the beginning of the pandemic. It is important to note that all information is taken directly from a regularly updated online database which gathers its information from health and government agencies such the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control, UN, and World Bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;featured-images-of-project&quot;&gt;Featured Images of Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/33791954/107155287-9d70b000-6945-11eb-9fa1-a39f50888760.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;gallery1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 1: The initial home screen&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/33791954/107155289-9ea1dd00-6945-11eb-9932-6996be54440b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;gallery2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 2: After searching up a specific country name&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/33791954/107155290-a06ba080-6945-11eb-895e-7fa4fa3bcb93.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;gallery3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 3: Data visualization graphs for each covid-19 fact&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-we-built-it&quot;&gt;How we built it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used various types of libraries and processes to aid in our program’s back-end. Requests was used extensively to retrieve data from the web in various formats such as json or html. The json was then dumped and formatted into a json file called &lt;strong&gt;data.json&lt;/strong&gt; and was then parsed later using the Pandas library to create dataframes for our data. We created various functions such as downloader, updater, and loader functions that deal with our data. We also created functions that manage our temporary files by efficiently deciding when to retrieve files from the web. All of this was then turned into a module called &lt;strong&gt;covid_data.py&lt;/strong&gt; that could be imported into the main python file that runs the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for our front-end, we used PyQt5 as our framework for our GUI.  We started of by templating and prototyping with the Qt Designer application so that we had a foundation to begin building our application upon. Once we were satisfied with a template, we converted it to python, and added more features to it later on. This code was then turned into a module called &lt;strong&gt;design.py&lt;/strong&gt; that could be imported into the main python file that runs the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our main python file, we created functions that could dynamically alter widgets in layouts as well as update values in them. We also used this file to bind buttons and labels to events and functions. The app’s entry point starts from this python file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges-we-ran-into&quot;&gt;Challenges we ran into&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matplotlib and pandas were libraries that seemed to us to have a major learning curve. We had challenges understanding how the library and its classes worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had issues integrating matplotlib with pyqt5. It was difficult to embed the plots into the layouts within the qt GUI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;accomplishments-that-were-proud-of&quot;&gt;Accomplishments that we’re proud of&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were able to make a project that was able to satisfy all of our initial goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Able to gather Covid-19 data from trustworthy sources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allow user to search which country they want to receive data from&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Created clear and organized user interface for users to view information&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Able to generate graphs based on gathered data&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-we-learned&quot;&gt;What we learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were able to learn about many different data science libraries and also got a bit of experience on how to use parts of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This hackathon also gave us the opportunity to force ourselves to go outside of our comfort zone and tackle new things in python and data management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next-for-covid-19-global&quot;&gt;What’s next for Covid-19 Global&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to speed up our application significantly by getting rid of excess nested function callings in our code as well as redundant variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well, in the future, we would like to package this application to be easily distributable to users of all major operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-order-to-run-this-code-until-further-updates-please-do-the-following&quot;&gt;In order to run this code until further updates, please do the following:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The following packages must be installed for this project to work:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bs4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;requests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pycountries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pyqt5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;matplotlib&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pandas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;datetime&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;qtmodern&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;re&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;os&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;json&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;afterwards, do the following command in terminal/cmd in the folder directory:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;python main.py
OR&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;python3 main.py&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="python" /><category term="qt" /><category term="webscraping" /><category term="pandas" /><category term="matplotlib" /><summary type="html">Get trustworthy current international facts and figures on Covid-19.</summary></entry></feed>
